ventrachicago.com 2015-03-17

# Privacy Policy | Ventra

The effective date of this Privacy Policy is August 14, 2013  
Last updated: August 14, 2013

**Overview**

The Chicago Transit Authority (CTA) and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies are committed to ensuring Ventra customer privacy and security.  Specifically: (1) CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies will not provide personal identifying information (PII) from Ventra accounts to any third party without express customer consent, except as described in this Privacy Policy; (2) PII from Ventraaccounts will never be provided to advertisers for their use; and (3) CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies will maintain a secure environment for customer PII.

This Privacy Policy is intended to provide an understanding of how CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies handle PII collected by the Ventra program.  Among other things, this policy explains the types of information collected from Ventra customers and the third parties with whom CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies may share this information.

CTA's contractor, Cubic Transportation Systems (the “Ventra Contractor”), is the primary operator of the Ventra Customer Service Center on behalf of CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies.  CTA oversees the Ventra Customer Service Center Contractor.  The Ventra User Agreement Terms and Conditions provides that by enrolling in the Ventra program and using the system, a customer allows CTA, the Ventra Customer Service Center Contractor, and other third parties referenced herein to process personal information according to the provisions set forth in the Ventra User Agreement Terms and Conditions and this Privacy Policy.

**Definitions**  
The following definitions apply:

·         **Personal Identifying Information (PII):** PII identifies or describes a person or can be directly linked to a specific individual. Examples of PII include, but are not limited to, a person's name, mailing address, billing address, business name, alternate contact information (if given), telephone number, e-mail address, fax number, Ventra Card serial number, credit or debit card number, security code and expiration date.

·         **Aggregate Data or Aggregate Information:** Aggregate Data or Aggregate Information is statistical information that is derived from collective data that relates to a group or category of persons from which PII has been obtained or collected.  Aggregate Data reflects the characteristics of a large group of anonymous people.  CTA may use Aggregate Data and provide Aggregate Data to others to generate statistical reports for the purpose of managing the Ventra Card and CTA’s and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies’ Ventra  program operations.

**Collection of Personal Identifying Information (PII)**  
A Ventra Account may either be registered or unregistered.  CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies, through the Ventra Customer Service Center, collect personal identifying information in order to register Ventra Accounts with the Ventra system.  Examples of personal identifying information include a Ventra cardholder's name, Ventra Card serial number, address, telephone number, email address, credit or debit card number and expiration date, or other information that personally identifies a Ventra cardholder.  CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies obtain this personal information from applications and other forms submitted by Ventra cardholders to the Ventra Customer Service Center by telephone, mail, facsimile transmission, in person, or by electronic submission through the Ventra website.  Data developed as a byproduct of the use of the Ventra system (e.g., a registered user's travel routes and times traveled) is also considered personal identifying information if a Ventra Account is registered.

**How CTA** **and Ventra Participating Transit AgenciesUse Personal Identifying Information**  
CTA uses PII provided by customers in order to effectively and efficiently process enrollments, manage accounts, respond to questions, send customer e-mails about Ventra program updates, and otherwise communicate with Ventra customers.

PII is only utilized as described in this Privacy Policy.

**Third Parties with Whom CTA** **and Ventra Participating Transit AgenciesMay Share Personal Identifying Information**  
CTA may share PII with any current or future Ventra Participating Transit Agencies including Pace Suburban Bus Service (Pace) for the purpose of operating and managing the Ventra program.  CTA and the Ventra Participating Transit Agencies may also disclose PII to the Regional Transportation Authority (RTA), Metra, and the Federal Transit Administration (FTA).  In the instance where another transit agency or party is added to the Ventra program, CTA will notify its customers via amendment to this Privacy Policy, as well as on its [general website](http://www.transitchicago.com/).  In addition, CTA and the Ventra Participating Transit Agencies may disclose PII to third party service providers for the purpose of operating and maintaining the Ventra system, such as managing customer accounts and collecting revenue.  These contractors are provided only with the PII they need to deliver the service being provided.  CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies require service providers to maintain the confidentiality of the information and to use it only as necessary to carry out their duties under the Ventra program.

CTA or the Ventra Contractor may share PII with the Illinois Attorney General or the United States Department of Justice or other governmental agencies with jurisdiction when necessary to respond to consumer complaints and to the extent required by law.  CTA or the Ventra Contractor may also share PII with the Illinois State Treasurer to the extent required by law.

CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies may provide a Ventra customer’s PII to a third party as necessary to process any retail transaction using a Ventra Card that a customer may conduct with retail merchants other than CTA or any Ventra Participating Transit Agencies.  As with any credit or debit card payment, if a Ventra customer conducts a transaction with a retail merchant using a Ventra pre-paid debit card*, Ventra mobile application, or any other Ventra program media, CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies need to share some information (for example, the customer’s name and credit or debit card number) with the banks and other entities in the financial system that process credit or debit card transactions.  CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies are not responsible for the third party use of PII provided to retail merchants at which customers use their Ventra pre-paid card, Ventra mobile application, or any other Ventra program media to conduct transactions, regardless of whether the transaction was conducted in person or online by the Ventra customer.  

Besides these entities, PII will not be disclosed to any other third party without express customer consent, except as required to comply with laws or legal process served on CTA, any current or future Ventra Participating Transit Agencies, or the Ventra Contractor.

**Retention of Personal Identifying Information**  
CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies, through the Ventra Contractor, shall only store the PII of a Ventra customer that is necessary to perform account functions such as billing, account settlement, or enforcement activities.  All PII will be discarded no later than seven years after a Ventra account is closed or terminated.

**Security of Ventra Personal Identifying Information**  
CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies are committed to the security of customer PII.  CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies, together with the Ventra Contractor, stores the PII provided by Ventra customers on computer servers that are located in secure, controlled facilities.  Servers are designed with software, hardware and physical security measures in place to prevent unauthorized access.

Access to PII is controlled through the following administrative, technical, and physical security measures.  By contract, third parties with whom CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies share PII are also required to implement adequate security measures to maintain the confidentiality of such information.

Administrative:

  * Access to PII is limited only to certain operations and technical employees for limited, approved purposes based on their specific work responsibilities necessary to the maintenance and operation of the Ventra program.
  * Privacy and security training is required for employees with access to PII, upon hire. In addition, regular periodic refresher training may be required for those employees.

Technical:

  * Ventra network perimeters are protected with firewalls.
  * All PII is protected using role-based access control.
  * Sensitive PII (e.g. credit or debit and bank account numbers) is encrypted when stored and when transmitted over public networks.
  * Electronic connections to and from the Ventra website are encrypted.
  * Vulnerability and penetration tests are conducted on the Ventra system.
  * CTA, the Ventra Participating Transit Agencies, and the Ventra Contractor employees' use of Ventra customer databases are monitored.

Physical:

  * Physical access to CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies and Ventra Contractor servers is restricted to authorized, administrative and technical personnel.
  * Data center access to approved administrative and technical personnel is restricted via passcode authentication and other security protocols.

**Ventra Customer Obligations and Legal Disclaimer**

In addition to CTA's and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies’ policies and procedures implementing PII security, the Ventra customer is responsible for safeguarding usernames, passwords, personal identification numbers (PINs), and other authentication information that may be used to access a Ventra account.  Ventra customers should not disclose authentication information to any third party and should notify CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies of any unauthorized use of their usernames or passwords.  CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies cannot secure PII that is released by Ventra customers to others or PII that customers request CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies to release to others. In addition, there is a risk that unauthorized third parties may engage in illegal activity, such as hacking into CTA's and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies’ security systems or the Ventra Contractor's security system, or by intercepting transmissions of personal information over the Internet.  CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies are not responsible for any data obtained in an unauthorized manner, and CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies are the only entity that may authorize obtaining data from the Ventra program by any third party.  CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies are also not responsible for any data or PII obtained by a third party as a result of a Ventra cardholder’s negligence or misuse of Ventra program fare media, products, or equipment.  In the instance where a Ventra cardholder’s fare media is lost, stolen, or damaged, CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies are not responsible for any data or PII that is obtained by a third party until the problem is reported to CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies as defined in the Ventra User Agreement.

Please note that the Ventra Contractor will never ask Ventra customers to provide or confirm any information in connection with Ventra such as credit card numbers, or other PII, unless the customer is logged into the secure Ventra customer website.  If a customer ever has any doubt about the authenticity of an e-mail regarding Ventra, the customer should open a new web browser, type in www.ventrachicago.com, log into the customer's Ventra account, and then perform the requested activity.

**Account Access and Controls**  
Registering a Ventra Account is in the customer's discretion.  Please see the Ventra User Agreement Terms and Conditions for information concerning the various benefits, protections, and potential fees associated with registering your Ventra Account.  The required account information consists of PII such as name, business name, mailing address(es), billing address, e-mail address, telephone number, fax number, signature, and credit or debit card number, expiration date and security code.  CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies may request other information as required by law.  CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies may request other optional information, such as alternate contact information, but in such instances CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies will clearly indicate that such information is optional.

Customers who have registered their Ventra Accounts can review and update personal account information at any time.  Customers are also able to modify, add, or delete any optional account information by signing into their Ventra Account and editing the account profile.  PII can also be reviewed and edited online as discussed below under "Updating Personal Identifying Information."  Ventra customers can close their account at any time by contacting Ventra Customer Service at (877) NOW-VENTRA.  All account information will be deleted no later than 7 years after an account is closed, terminated, or left inactive by the customer.  See the Ventra User Agreement Terms and Conditions for more information on the requirements of customer account maintenance.

**Aggregate Data**

CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies may also combine the PII provided by Ventra customers in a non-identifiable format with other information to create Aggregate Data that may be disclosed to third parties.  Aggregate Data is used by CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies to improve the Ventra program and for the marketing of Ventra.  Aggregate Data does not contain any information that could be used to contact or identify individual Ventra customers or their accounts.  For example, CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies may inform third parties regarding the number of Ventra accounts within a particular zip code.  CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies require third parties with whom Aggregate Data is shared to agree that they will not attempt to make information personally identifiable, such as by combining it with other databases.

**Cookies**  
The Ventra website, www.ventrachicago.com, stores "cookies" on the computer systems of users of the website.  Cookies are small data elements that a website can store on a user's system.

The cookies used by the Ventra web site facilitate customers’ use of the website (e.g., by remembering login names and passwords until the session has ended).  The Ventra website does not require that users of the website accept these cookies.  Additionally, the Ventra website does not store "third party" cookies on the computer systems of users of the website.

Once a site user leaves the Ventra website, the privacy policy of other websites visited or linked to from the Ventra website should be reviewed to understand how these external sites utilize cookies and how the information that is collected through the use of cookies on those websites is utilized.

CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies do not knowingly engage in business with any company or vendor that uses Spyware or Malware.  CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies do not market detailed information collected from web sessions that can be directly tied to personal information.  Further, CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies do not provide Ventra customers with downloadable software that collects or utilizes any PII.

**Third Party Websites and Applications**  
The Ventra website contains links to third party websites operated by entities that are affiliated with the Ventra program.  These web links may be referenced within content, or placed beside the names or logos of the other entities.  CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies do not disclose PII to these third party websites except as described in this Privacy Policy.

**WARNING: Once a patron enters external websites or applications (whether through a service or content link), CTA** **and Ventra Participating Transit Agenciesare not responsible for the privacy practices of external websites or applications.**  Please review all privacy policies of external websites or applications before providing any information to external websites or applications.

**Updating Personal Identifying Information**  
PII can be reviewed and edited online at www.ventrachicago.com.  In addition, customers may update their PII by telephoning the Ventra Customer Call Center at (877) NOW-VENTRA.

Complaints or problems regarding updating personal information should be submitted via the Ventra website.  The Ventra Customer Service Center will either resolve the issue or forward the complaint to an appropriate CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies staff member for a response or resolution.  CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies strive to answer all queries within 48 business hours, but it may not always be feasible to do so.

If an adequate resolution is not received, please contact CTA at:  

Chicago Transit Authority

Attn:  Ventra Customer Service Center                                 

567 West Lake Street

Chicago, IL 60661

E-mail: [webmaster@transitchicago.com](mailto:webmaster@transitchicago.com)

**Changes to this Privacy Policy**

CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies reserve the right to modify this Privacy Policy at any time without notice.  When CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies revise this Privacy Policy, the "last updated" date at the top of the Privacy Policy will reflect the date of the last change.  We encourage Ventra customers to review this Privacy Policy periodically to stay informed about how CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies protect the security of PII collected for the Ventra program.  Continued use of the Ventra program constitutes the customer's agreement to this Privacy Policy and any updates.

**E-mails Sent to CTA** **and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies**  
This Privacy Policy does not apply to the content of e-mails transmitted directly to CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies. Please do not send PII in an email directly to CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies.  For more information on how CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies protect the content of e-mails correspondence transmitted to and from CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies, please click [here](http://www.transitchicago.com/privacy.aspx).

**Contact Information**  
CTA and Ventra Participating Transit Agencies welcomes comments on the Ventra Privacy Policy.  Please e-mail comments to [webmaster@transitchicago.com](mailto:webmaster@transitchicago.com).

* * *

*Customers using the Ventra pre-paid debit card should refer to the privacy policy of MetaBank™, the issuer of the Ventra pre-paid debit card.
